<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-17T21:55:49+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Learning Repository</title><subtitle>Personal thoughts on what I see around. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on the metaverse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/17/metaverse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on the metaverse" /><published>2023-04-17T21:54:32+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-17T21:54:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/17/metaverse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/17/metaverse.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been using the Oculus Quest 2, on and off for about 1 year now. The first time I used it I was blown away. I thought to myself, this is definitely the future. Weirdly enough, when I discussed it with my friends and even the reviews online, no one particularly seems to enjoy it. “It’s a poorly designed gaming system” - this is the typical response that I got. Later in this post, I will delve into potential enhancements for broader adoption, as well as fundamental paradigm shifts that may be necessary.</p>

<p>The virtual and augmented reality (AR/VR) industry has plummeted from investors’ radar due to lackluster sales figures of Meta and with highly anticipated startups like Magic Leap failing to meet expectations by a significant margin. Top tech personalities like Elon Musk have also said that “I don’t see someone strapping a friggin’ screen to their face all day”. John Carmack who was in charge of building the metaverse left Meta saying that the pace of innovation is slow.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<video width="80%" preload="auto" muted="" controls="" style="margin: auto;">
    <source src="/asset/videos/bigscreen_ss.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>
<p><br /></p>

<p>This is a short screen capture that I did in the VR and it felt like I was really there. The discussions in VR are very different from what one experiences in group chats or group calls. There really is an immersive feel to it. But it comes at a cost, when you enter the metaverse you become completely disconnected from the actual world. So unlike on a group video call, you can’t quickly share/access your files on your computer/mobile or the internet. You can’t hear your mom yelling for you to come down. For a little amount of immersion, it feels that we sacrifice a large amount of control and awareness. This can be both good and bad depending on the circumstances, but ideally, it’s good for things that require less control. For e.g. watching movies, sitting in a group and just discussing random topics, or playing a game where all the controls are already present in the VR. For most of the day-to-day work, it would be difficult to migrate to VR.</p>

<p>One other issue is that very few of your friends are in it. Even if they are, there are very few things to be done. We already have MMORPGs and similar games, where your network is present and the ‘immersive’ experience doesn’t make much difference. As stated in “The cold start problem”, the goal should be to first build an atomic network and then grow from there. I believe Meta had the right idea, of focusing on creating VR-first experiences. It can be a game but mostly has to be something different. Maybe it’s a field trip to an alien planet with your friends, maybe it’s an escape room, or a VR documentary. I believe BigScreenVR has found its core group of users (like me), who tune in every now and then. What’s their secret sauce? They let anyone host a private room and share any video. So you could in ‘theory’ have ‘some’ people screening the latest movies and you get to watch it from a perfect spot in a grand theatre without a kid crying in the back.</p>

<p>User experience is the other thing that creates a lot of friction. First, you have to put on the clunky headsets in position then turn them on then wait for them to boot. If in between you have to go to the bathroom, you have to take the entire thing off (headsets, controllers, charging cables, headphones, and wires) and then put it back on when you come back. The headset should be small, super quick to boot (or maybe should plug in directly to your laptop), have a long battery life or charges through the laptop connection, and has just simple gloves for hand tracking (no turning on or battery required for those). I believe one other limitation is the technology, current graphics look like they are from the PS2 era. As Apple has been always great at striking the balance between tech and user experience, I believe they have the most chance of nailing this correctly. We will have to wait and see what Apple unveils in June.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been using the Oculus Quest 2, on and off for about 1 year now. The first time I used it I was blown away. I thought to myself, this is definitely the future. Weirdly enough, when I discussed it with my friends and even the reviews online, no one particularly seems to enjoy it. “It’s a poorly designed gaming system” - this is the typical response that I got. Later in this post, I will delve into potential enhancements for broader adoption, as well as fundamental paradigm shifts that may be necessary.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">System Design of my social media app</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/12/unfiltr_system_design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="System Design of my social media app" /><published>2023-04-12T22:55:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-12T22:55:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/12/unfiltr_system_design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/12/unfiltr_system_design.html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year me and my friend started a startup. We started with a BNPL app but shortly after that the revised RBI guidelines came to effect and all our plans were thrown into disarray and we had to pivot to a different idea altogether. In a desperate attempt to catch the billion-dollar wave of BeReal, we pivoted to make a BeReal clone for the Indian market (I know this was one of the worst pivots a startup with our circumstances can take). As we started building the app I realized it was not as simple as it seems. Since I was leading the tech, I had to figure out a lot of the stuff. In this article, I will summarize the high-level system design that I followed to build our MVP.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/unfiltr_2.webp" alt="App Screenshot" style="max-height: 600px; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Let’s start with the tech challenges that we needed to solve.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Feed should load as quickly as possible</li>
  <li>Reactions and comments should also be visible with minimal delay</li>
  <li>Feed should be customized per user (just basic personalization for now)</li>
</ul>

<p>Remember, this was just an MVP and we only had about a month and a half to roll everything out, so some of the solutions might seem a little hackish but it worked for us. Since this was a read-heavy system we cached most of the stuff. All the posts were updated in follower feeds and directly served from the cache after a couple of joins.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/tweet_normal_user.png" alt="Tweet update" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>One drawback with this approach is that if a user has a large number of followers this update can be slow. Therefore to tackle that, what we did was to update the celebrity posts at the time of fetching the user feed. We checked what celebrities the user is following and then added their most recent post in the user feed. In larger systems, there might be a completely separate logic for handling which post should be added (maybe it’s the most interesting to the user or with the most number of likes or a mix of the two).</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/celebrity_user.png" alt="Tweet update" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>For storing reactions and comments we used the same formula. We cached most of the stuff. Whenever an update was made we updated both the SQL and the cache. Normally when the system scales, these SQL updates will need to be batched or else it will overtax the DB. We followed a simple schema for storing these.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/reaction_cache_schema.png" alt="Cache Schema" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Now for customizing the main user feed we kept it simple. Ideally, different ML pipelines work over the interaction data of the user along with other parameters to achieve this. But we just gave a score to different interaction events like tap, share, comment, and like and generated a rank based on the weighted score (just making an MVP here). The interaction data was put in a Kinesis stream and then in intervals of 30 minutes, the data was batched and written into S3 files. Our backend would pick this data at regular intervals and update the post scores.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/kinesis_data.png" alt="Kinesis update" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Apart from this, there were other optimizations like batching the notifications when it exceeds a particular threshold, converting profile images to lower resolution for loading thumbnails, making a Jenkins task trigger at a random time, etc. To keep things streamlined we used Terraform for managing the infra. This was my second time working this it and I was really impressed by how much efficient it was compared to manually tinkering with the GUI.</p>

<p>Though I enjoyed working on the project, we couldn’t make it grow. Social media is one of my favorite fields to work in and I hope I get a chance to make something worthwhile in the future.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last year me and my friend started a startup. We started with a BNPL app but shortly after that the revised RBI guidelines came to effect and all our plans were thrown into disarray and we had to pivot to a different idea altogether. In a desperate attempt to catch the billion-dollar wave of BeReal, we pivoted to make a BeReal clone for the Indian market (I know this was one of the worst pivots a startup with our circumstances can take). As we started building the app I realized it was not as simple as it seems. Since I was leading the tech, I had to figure out a lot of the stuff. In this article, I will summarize the high-level system design that I followed to build our MVP.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Race for an AI marketplace</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/07/race-for-ai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Race for an AI marketplace" /><published>2023-04-07T20:44:32+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-07T20:44:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/07/race-for-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/07/race-for-ai.html"><![CDATA[<p>AI research is going so fast that even the adult industry is having a tough time catching up. Every day there’s a brand new paper on different AI architecture and yesterday I saw a paper by HuggingFace for a model that can communicate with all the different models present on the platform and with time will learn what model to use with what query. It’s moving fast enough to convince many top tech people that we will reach AGI in the next 5 years! that’s wild. Although I feel we might still have a decade or so before we reach there, but we can definitely get pretty close in the next couple of years.</p>

<p>So what’s next in AI? I believe the next goal is to make it much more integrated into our life. We want AI to take care of our finances, groceries, research, entertainment, and life in general. We want a PERSONAL ASSISTANT in our pocket. There will be a unified layer that will communicate through all the different oracles and entities on our behalf of us. For this layer to be personal and intimate, it can’t be just any other piece of technology it has to feel personal. OpenAI has figured this out and is going for the takedown.</p>

<p><img src="/asset/images/ai_landscape.png" alt="AI Landscape" /></p>

<p>You must be thinking, but wait a minute OpenAI doesn’t have an AI with personality. I think it’s going to have one very soon. Look at the tweet below.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Startups developing AI characters lookout. Filled this OpenAI survey and I think I know what&#39;s next. <a href="https://t.co/uStZNpLLUg">pic.twitter.com/uStZNpLLUg</a></p>&mdash; Piyush Kumar (@thisispiyushK) <a href="https://twitter.com/thisispiyushK/status/1644247755483754496?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 7, 2023</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>Obviously, there won’t be just one company with this powerful AI, and seeing the pace of development it is very much possible that developers would be able to create their own AI for niche use cases. The good strategy therefore could be to aggregate these niche AIs on a single platform. This marketplace won’t be competing with the likes of OpenAI, Meta, or Google. Quora released it’s own platform <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/02/06/quora-opens-its-new-ai-chatbot-app-poe-to-the-general-public/">Poe</a> a couple of months back and recently <a href="https://www.fixie.ai/">Fixie</a>, a startup in the similar direction picked up $17 million in funding</p>

<p>Who wins the AI wars is yet to be seen. It could very easily be the case that going above the current reasoning capacity of GPT-4 is not even possible with neural nets or that the entire internet’s data is not enough to train the next big AI. I will be following this space and will be sharing some small projects that I am building along the way.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AI research is going so fast that even the adult industry is having a tough time catching up. Every day there’s a brand new paper on different AI architecture and yesterday I saw a paper by HuggingFace for a model that can communicate with all the different models present on the platform and with time will learn what model to use with what query. It’s moving fast enough to convince many top tech people that we will reach AGI in the next 5 years! that’s wild. Although I feel we might still have a decade or so before we reach there, but we can definitely get pretty close in the next couple of years.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Draft - System Design of my social media app</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/draft-copy-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Draft - System Design of my social media app" /><published>2023-04-01T20:44:32+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-01T20:44:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/draft%20copy%202</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/draft-copy-2.html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year me and my friend started a startup. We started with a BNPL app but shortly after that the revised RBI guidelines came to effect and all our plans were thrown into disarray and we had to pivot to a different idea altogether. In a desperate attempt to catch the billion-dollar wave of BeReal, we pivoted to make a BeReal clone for the Indian market (I know this was one of the worst pivots a startup with our circumstances can take). As we started building the app I realized it was not as simple as it seems. Since I was leading the tech, I had to figure out a lot of the stuff. In this article, I will summarize the high-level system design that I followed to build our MVP.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/unfiltr_2.webp" alt="App Screenshot" style="max-height: 600px; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Let’s start with the tech challenges that we needed to solve.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Feed should load as quickly as possible</li>
  <li>Reactions and comments should also be visible with minimal delay</li>
  <li>Feed should be customized per user (just basic personalization for now)</li>
</ul>

<p>Remember, this was just an MVP and we only had about a month and a half to roll everything out, so some of the solutions might seem a little hackish but it worked for us. Since this was a read-heavy system we cached most of the stuff. All the posts were updated in follower feeds and directly served from the cache after a couple of joins.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/tweet_normal_user.png" alt="Tweet update" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>One drawback with this approach is that if a user has a large number of followers this update can be slow. Therefore to tackle that, what we did was to update the celebrity posts at the time of fetching the user feed. We checked what celebrities the user is following and then added their most recent post in the user feed. In larger systems, there might be a completely separate logic for handling which post should be added (maybe it’s the most interesting to the user or with the most number of likes or a mix of the two).</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/celebrity_user.png" alt="Tweet update" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>For storing reactions and comments we used the same formula. We cached most of the stuff. Whenever an update was made we updated both the SQL and the cache. Normally when the system scales, these SQL updates will need to be batched or else it will overtax the DB. We followed a simple schema for storing these.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/reaction_cache_schema.png" alt="Cache Schema" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Now for customizing the main user feed we kept it simple. Ideally, different ML pipelines work over the interaction data of the user along with other parameters to achieve this. But we just gave a score to different interaction events like tap, share, comment, and like and generated a rank based on the weighted score (just making an MVP here). The interaction data was put in a Kinesis stream and then in intervals of 30 minutes, the data was batched and written into S3 files. Our backend would pick this data at regular intervals and update the post scores.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/asset/images/kinesis_data.png" alt="Kinesis update" style="height: 100%; max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;" />
</div>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Apart from this, there were other optimizations like batching the notifications when it exceeds a particular threshold, converting profile images to lower resolution for loading thumbnails, making a Jenkins task trigger at a random time, etc. Though I enjoyed working on the project, we couldn’t make it grow. Social media is one of my favorite fields to work in and I hope I get a chance to make something worthwhile in the future.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last year me and my friend started a startup. We started with a BNPL app but shortly after that the revised RBI guidelines came to effect and all our plans were thrown into disarray and we had to pivot to a different idea altogether. In a desperate attempt to catch the billion-dollar wave of BeReal, we pivoted to make a BeReal clone for the Indian market (I know this was one of the worst pivots a startup with our circumstances can take). As we started building the app I realized it was not as simple as it seems. Since I was leading the tech, I had to figure out a lot of the stuff. In this article, I will summarize the high-level system design that I followed to build our MVP.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Draft - Tumblr’s decline</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/draft-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Draft - Tumblr’s decline" /><published>2023-04-01T20:44:32+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-01T20:44:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/draft%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/draft-copy.html"><![CDATA[<ol>
  <li>
    <p>the current state of metaverse
 i. My experience
 ii. Plans of the big players
 iii. Startups in stealth</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>what’s missing
 i. John carmack leaving meta
 ii. Time saying they were wrong
 iii. Low graphic video game</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>how to improve
 i. gaming is the first step
 ii. strong social media (zero cost) -&gt; paid weak social media
 iii. things that replace reality quite well (movies, tv series, growth)
 iv. path to growth (provide utility -&gt; form networks/ community -&gt; engage)</p>
  </li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the current state of metaverse i. My experience ii. Plans of the big players iii. Startups in stealth]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Attention is all you need</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/attention-is-all-you-need.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Attention is all you need" /><published>2023-04-01T20:44:32+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-01T20:44:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/attention-is-all-you-need</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/04/01/attention-is-all-you-need.html"><![CDATA[<p>With tech tutorials flooding the streaming platforms and every next person you meet being a software developer (or planning to become one),
technology is getting commoditized. At least the ones over which the current multi-billion dollar platforms are built upon. We find ourselves in a
sea of open-source projects, all built with the same building blocks in some sense. It didn’t take LLMs long to figure out the patterns
and start coding in a near-human level capacity. The future may still be a little further when anyone who wants to code, can code. But we are
almost there, as almost anyone who wants to code can code and build products right now. Knowledge is available for free on the Internet.</p>

<p>Whatever a small team can build, a giant organization or someone else can build very easily as well (with some exceptions). And this is a common practice, follow a small startup, and if the idea sounds interesting enough just copy it. I realized this when I made a small website summarization plugin using OpenAI APIs, and although there were a lot of plugins already available only a few were with the most downloads and were getting shared everywhere. The key is to differentiate. And to differentiate you need attention. If a guy with 100K followers releases a beta, he instantly gets 50-100 customers while a guy with a much better product gets 1-2 and 
they churn out eventually. In this day and age, attention is one of the very strong moats any business can have. Whether it’s a newsletter, YouTube 
channel, or Twitter account, as long as it has the right audience it has a potential revenue stream.</p>

<p>Big businesses (especially big tech) have realized this and are buying media houses left and right. Hustle’s acquisition by Hubspot is an example of this. Although big businesses don’t have to worry too much about generating revenue but having a media arm that connects with the audience in a genuine manner is very important. People see an ad from a mile away. This is the new approach of creating a community, buy an existing one. The smart move for current entrepreneurs I believe too is to create a community that they can monetize or at the very least try to develop a following.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With tech tutorials flooding the streaming platforms and every next person you meet being a software developer (or planning to become one), technology is getting commoditized. At least the ones over which the current multi-billion dollar platforms are built upon. We find ourselves in a sea of open-source projects, all built with the same building blocks in some sense. It didn’t take LLMs long to figure out the patterns and start coding in a near-human level capacity. The future may still be a little further when anyone who wants to code, can code. But we are almost there, as almost anyone who wants to code can code and build products right now. Knowledge is available for free on the Internet.]]></summary></entry></feed>